<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Chrome-devtools | Octoblog]]></title>
  <link href="http://niki4810.github.com/blog/categories/chrome-devtools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://niki4810.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-13T22:18:15-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://niki4810.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nikhilesh Katakam]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing gulp-devtools]]></title>
    <link href="http://niki4810.github.com/blog/2014/12/13/introducing-gulp-devtools/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-13T21:46:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://niki4810.github.com/blog/2014/12/13/introducing-gulp-devtools</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Its been a while since my previous blog post and I am very happy to finally made some time to blog agian. Recently I have been playing a lot with <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/extensions/getstarted">chrome extension</a> development as its so much fun.<!-- more --></p>

<p>Chrome provides a very easy and neat way to re-use your existing web development skills to write powerful extensions and apps. These app can be published onto the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/category/apps">chrome web store</a> and can be dowloaded onto any chrome browser.</p>

<p>As a part of this learning process I happen to create my first chrome extension called <a href="http://niki4810.github.io/gulp-devtools/">gulp-devtools</a>.</p>

<p>gulp-devtools, is simple chrome extension, that lets you run your gulp tasks from within your chrome browser via a UI. The below image shows a demo of gulp-devtools</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/niki4810/gulp-devtools/gh-pages/gulp-devtools-gif.gif" alt="alt tag" /></p>

<p>Its provides some cool features to search through a list of all the gulp tasks in your project, start/stop a gulp task and run gulp tasks in the background (useful for tasks like watch).</p>

<p>You can download the extension via the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/gulp-devtools/ojpmgjhofceebfifeajnjojpokebkkji">chrome web store</a>. If you'd like to contribute to it on see the latest on this plugin development, you can checkout the <a href="https://github.com/niki4810/gulp-devtools">github repo</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
